BOB WEEK

Computational Biologist

SUMMARY —

I am interested in applying my background in mathematical and computational methods to solve difficult problems faced by industry. My experience makes me uniquely positioned to develop and analyze simulations and models used to optimize industrial processes.

**** 360 216 9074 **** github.com/bobweek

♀ Beaverton, Oregon in /in/bobweek/

SKILLS

Software: Julia, Python, R, Linux, Mathematica,

SLURM, C/C++, Matlab

Math: Linear Algebra, Dynamical Systems,

Harmonic Analysis, Stochastic Processes

Statistics: Modeling, Analysis, Inference

(e.g., GLM, PCA, MCMC, KDE, ABC, GRF)

EXPERIENCE -

2022 - Current Postdoctoral Research Fellow

B.J.M. Bohannan Lab, University of Oregon

- · I developed a novel mathematical framework to understand microbiome-mediated host evolution
 - · This is the first time such a genralization has been formally carried out
 - · Conceptually novel by formally generalizing biological inheritance using path analysis
 - · Requisite background is basic calculus, which facilitates communication with biologists
- I developed microbially-explicit individual-based **simulations** to test the mathematical framework
 - \cdot I chose Julia for fast implementation, JIT-compilation, and ease of parallelization
- · I implented multi-threading on a computational cluster in Julia to compare theory and simulations
 - · Multi-threading was necessary to overcome time constraints
- The mathematical framework and associated simulation model is under review at RoySocB
 - · Code for the simulation model is available here
- · I developed a novel genetically-explicit spatial host-microbe simulation model in Julia
 - · The model is novel by adding explicit genome evolution and host spatial structure
 - · I chose Julia for fast implementation, JIT-compilation, and ease of parallelization
 - · To improve simulation performance, I used sparse matrices to represent genomic data
 - · Code for this simulation model is available here

2020 - 2022 Postdoctoral Researcher

G. Bradburd Lab, Michigan State University

- · Applied SVD (singular value decomposition) to simulate multivariate Gaussian fields in Julia
 - · I chose SVD instead of **Cholesky** because high numerical stability was required
 - · I chose Julia because of fast implementation
- · I applied FFT in NumPy to analyze coherence of simulated genomic data
 - · I chose this approach to identify the spatial signature of coevolution on genomic data
 - · I chose NumPy because Python also has tools for efficient analysis of genomic data
- I used **SLURM** to schedule large-scale simulations on a High-Performance Computing Cluster
- · I developed an individual-based model of spatial host-parasite coevolution
 - · I then implemented this model using the *SLiM* simulation framework
 - \cdot I also used this model to derive an **SPDE** model and analytical results using **Fourier analysis**
- · I published the SPDE model in a recent paper available here
- · Code for the simulation model is available here

2015 - 2020 **Doctoral Student**

S.L. Nuismer Lab, University of Idaho

- · I developed heuristics to calculate population-level models from individual-based models
 - · This is useful for **analyzing simulations** and deriving mechanistic analytical models
- I developed heuristics using infinite-dimensional stochastic analysis to calculate SDE from SPDE
- · I applied the above heuristics to generalize existing eco-evolutionary mathematical frameworks
 - · I published this framework here
 - · Code associated with this framework is available here
- I developed a model-based maximum likelihood method to measure species coevolution
 - \cdot This required developing a model of coevolution yielding a tractable likelihood function
 - · I implemented this method in R to make it accessible for empirical biologists
 - · I published this project here
- I applied my framework to study the coevolutionary maintence of mutualism, published here

SELECTED PROJECTS ————————————————————————————————————	
2023	The Evolution of Microbiome-Mediated Traits Analytical and simulation models of host trait evolution mediated by microbiome transmission
2023	Host-Parasite Coevolution in Continuous Space zenodo.org/records/8008017 A stochastic partial differential equation model for spatial analysis of host-parasite coevolution
2022	The Genomic Signature of Coevolution github.com/bobweek/genomic-sign-coev-cont-sp Individual-based simulations of coevolution and spatial analysis of simulated genomic data
2021	White Noise Evolutionary Ecology github.com/bobweek/white.noise.community.ecology An application of infinite-dimensional stochastic calculus to unify eco-evolutionary models
2019	Measuring Coevolution github.com/bobweek/measuring.coevolution A maximum likelihood method to measure coevolution using spatial trait data
EDUCATION —	
2020	PhD Bioinformatics & Computational Biology S.L. Nuismer Lab, University of Idaho Dissertation focused on modeling eco-evolutionary processes and developing statistical methods
2015	BS Mathematics Traditional math degree with electives Digital Logic, Signals & Systems, Physics, and Numerical Methods
AWARDS -	
2018 - 2019	Bioinformatics & Computational Biology Fellowship Project aimed to model the duration of coevolutionary associations
2017-2018	Bioinformatics & Computational Biology Fellowship Project aimed to develop a method to measure coevolution in continuous space
2017	Paul Joyce Memorial BCB Fellowship Endowment Nominated by Professor Scott Nuismer because of my "love for mathematics and helping others to appreciate how it can be used to understand biological processes"
2013-2015	Undergraduate Research in Biology & Mathematics Efforts focused on developing a method to measure coevolution in discrete space